Guide to the Stevens Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stevens family papers
1777-1870
GEN MSS 1027
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.6
(11 boxes)
The collection contains Ebenezer Stevens' correspondence and documents, and nine financial account books for the firm of Ebenezer Stevens' Sons. The correspondence primarily relates to Stevens' military service and cohort including Horatio Gates, and his relationships with Antigua merchants Thomas Norbury Kerby and Samuel Byam Athill; also present are letters from Robert Liston, Britain's minister plenipotentiary to the United States. Other papers include Ebenezer Stevens' military appointment certificate, a petition on behalf of a political appointment for John Murray Forbes, and a manuscript map of the military installations around Fort Erie in Ontario, Canada. The collection is accompanied by three early twentieth-century reproductions featuring images of Ebenezer Stevens.
Stevens family
Stevens, Ebenezer, 1751-1823
Ebenezer Stevens' Sons
General note
The Ebenezer Stevens' Sons account books bear the labels of New York stationers Francis & Loutrel and Slote & Janes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ebenezer Stevens (1751-1823)
Born in Roxbury in 1751, Ebenezer Stevens joined a Boston artillery company in 1768 at the age of seventeen; five years later, the company took part in the Boston Tea Party. An officer in the Revolutionary War, he fought at the battle of Bunker Hill under Major General Horatio Gates, played a key role at Saratoga, and served under Lafayette in Virginia and at Yorktown. After the Revolution Stevens settled in New York and became a prominent merchant in the West Indian and Caribbean trade, importing and selling rum, brandies, wines, gins, and other alcoholic beverages. He also pursued a political career as a member of the New York State Assembly. Having attained the grade of major general of the artillery of the state of New York, he participated in the battle of Fort Erie and left military service in 1814.
Stevens was married in 1774 to Rebecca Hodgdon, daughter of Benjamin Hodgdon, and with her had four children: Elizabeth (1775-1777); Horatio Gates (1778-1873, married Eliza Lucille Rhinelander); Rebecca Hodgdon (1780-1815, married John Peter Schermerhorn); and George Alexander (1782-1807). His second wife was Lucretia Ledyard Sands, with whom he had seven children: Samuel (1785-1844, Yale 1804); William (1787-1867); Alexander Hodgdon (1789-1869, Yale 1807, married three times: Mary Jane Bayard, Catherine Morris, and Phoebe Coles Lloyd); Byam Kerby (1792-1870, Yale 1811, married Frances Gallatin); John Austin (1795-1874, Yale 1813, married Abby Weld); Henry Hewgill (1797-1869, married Catherine Clarkson Crosby); and Mary Lucretia (1798-1877, married Frederick William Rhinelander).
In 1818 Byam Kerby Stevens and John Austin Stevens joined their father in business as Ebenezer Stevens & Sons, and continued the firm as Ebenezer Stevens' Sons after his death in 1823. Byam Kerby Stevens bought the firm and its name from his brother John in 1862; it closed with his death in 1870.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1777-1820. II. Account Books, 1846-1870.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Ebenezer Stevens' correspondence and documents, nine financial account books for the firm of Ebenezer Stevens' Sons, and three early twentieth-century reproductions of portraits of Ebenezer Stevens. The correspondence primarily relates to Stevens' military service; exceptions include twelve letters from Thomas Norbury Kerby (1758-1819), a merchant in Antigua, one letter from Stevens to Kerby's partner Samuel Byam Athill (1758-1832), and five letters from Robert Liston (1742-1836), Britain's envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary to the United States. Other Papers contains military related material including a manuscript map of the installations around Fort Erie in Ontario, Canada.
Imports -- New York (State) -- New York; Merchants -- New York (State) -- New York; Antigua -- Commerce -- United States; Ontario -- Fort Erie -- Maps; United States -- Commerce -- Antigua and Barbuda -- Antigua; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783 -- Personal narratives, American; Account books -- New York (State) -- New York -- 19th century; Booksellers' labels (Provenance) -- Francis & Loutrel, New York; Booksellers' labels (Provenance) -- Slote & Janes, New York; Military maps -- Ontario -- Fort Erie -- 19th century; Merchants -- New York (State) -- New York -- 19th century; Athill, Samuel Byam; Forbes, John Murray, 1771-1831; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; Kerby, Thomas Norbury, 1758-1819; Liston, Robert, Sir, 1742-1836; Stevens, Byam Kerby, 1792-1870; Stevens, Ebenezer, 1751-1823; Stevens family; Stevens, John Austin, 1795-1874; Ebenezer Stevens' Sons
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1777-1820; Series I; 0.33; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence primarily relating to Ebenezer Stevens' military and merchant careers. Documents are related to Stevens' military career, with three early twentieth-century reproductions of images of him.
  - Correspondence
    - Ayrigg, Benjamin, 1807 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Athill, Samuel Byam
    - Bleecker, John, 1807 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C. G. Barrillon & Co., 1817 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Constant, Joseph, 1806 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Forbes, R. B., 1807 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gates, Horatio, 1777-1806 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      General note
      Contains one letter from Gates, with drafts of Stevens' statement in presentation of colors to the Saratoga Rangers on behalf of Gates, and an order from Stevens to Gates regarding the drafting of blacksmiths for the Continental Army.
    - Irving, P., 1800 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Kerby, Thomas Norbury, 1792-1817 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Laurence, William, 1810 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Liston, Robert, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Loring, John, 1806 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - North, William, 1818 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Pickering, Timothy, 1811 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pintard, John, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pleasanton, Stephen, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      With statement of account between the Stevens and the United States.
    - Preston, Remember, 1796 Jan 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Rhea, Jonathan, 1807 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Spencer, John C., 1808 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Stevens, Byam Kerby, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Stevens, Ebenezer, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Contains on letter of introduction for Byam K. Stevens to Samuel Athill in Antigua and two letters to Byam K. Stevens in St. Kitts.
    - Stevens, George A., 1811 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stevens, John A., 1820 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Tompkins, Daniel D., 1808 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Trumbull, John, 1794 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Wallace, William, 1808 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Ward, Joshua, 1807 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Other Papers
    - Certificate of appointment as Lieutenant Colonel, second battalion of artillery, Army of the United States, 1780 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Return of Officers, listing officers' names and the time of their appointment, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Petition for appointment of John Murray Forbes as consul at Havre de Grace, France, 1801 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Announcement of the establishment of Ebenezer Stevens & Sons, 1818 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Account current between Ebenezer Stevens and Samuel Hodgdon, 1777-1778 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Manuscript map of the military installations at Fort Erie, Ontario, circa 1814 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Engraved portrait of Ebenezer Stevens by J. J. Cade, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Photograph of oil portrait of Ebenezer Stevens, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Reproduction of John Trumbull's mural of the surrender of General Burgoyne at Saratoga, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Kerby, Thomas Norby, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Contains two oversize letters.
- Account Books, 1846-1870; Series II; 2.25; (9 boxes)
  The series contains nine bound volumes of financial records for the Ebenezer Stevens' Sons firm but also include some family accounts. Titles are taken from the spines of each volume; they bear paper labels of the New York stationers Francis & Loutrel and Slote & Janes.
  - Accounts Current "D", 1846-1856 (Box 3)
  - Accounts Current "E", 1857-1868 (Box 4)
  - Cash Book "I", 1853-1858 (Box 5)
  - Cash Book "K", 1858-1864 (Box 6)
  - Day Book "N", 1852-1858 (Box 7)
  - Day Book "BKS", 1859-1866 (Box 8)
    Opening page contains notice of dissolution of Ebenezer Stevens' Sons (October 31, 1862) clipped from newspaper.
  - Journal "I", 1849-1858 (Box 9)
  - Journal "K", 1859-1870 (Box 10)
  - Ledger, 1859-1870 (Box 11)